Finding Aid for Clara H. Brucker papers, 1920-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clara H. Brucker papers
1920-1980
Brucker, Clara H.
8558 Aa 2
Active in numerous civic and charitable organization, Clara Brucker assisted her husband Wilber M. Brucker, who had served as both governor of Michigan and Secretary of the Army. The collection includes correspondence, speeches, travel briefs and diaries.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
8 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Clara Brucker (donor no. 3767 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Clara H. Brucker was born in Iowa, then moved to Michigan where she graduated from Saginaw High School. Although teaching was her first love, she decided on a business career when the First World War broke out. After graduation from Drexel Institute she became a statistician for Du Pont and later for General Motors in New York, where she also studied magazine writing at Columbia.
In 1923 she married Wilber Brucker, then Prosecuting Attorney of Saginaw County, later to become Attorney General and Governor of Michigan, as well as Secretary of the Army. In the early 1930s, Clara Brucker received her B.A. in economics and M.A. in political science from Michigan State College.
Throughout her life, Clara Brucker was involved in many activities and organizations, including the School of Government, which she organized in 1940 and headed for over twenty years; the Detroit Children's Aid Society; the International YWCA; the auxiliary of Rainbow Division Veterans; and the Republican Auxiliary. In Washington she was Chairman of the Endowment Fund of the Soldiers', Sailors', Marines' and Airmen's Club.
The Clara Brucker collection includes papers concerning her work with the Mock Republican Conventions and her interest in the prevention of sex crimes against women and children, the General Federation of Women's Clubs and miscellaneous other charities. One of Clara Brucker's correspondents was May-ling Soong Chiang (Mme. Chiang Kai-shek). The collection has been arranged into the following series: Personal and biographical; School of Government; Women's civic, political and service organizations; Clippings; Travel and trip briefings; Diaries; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-2003.; Detroit School of Government.; Detroit School of Government. Mock Republican Convention.; General Federation of Women's Clubs.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; Republican Party (Mich.); Sex crimes.; Social service--United States--Societies, etc.; Women--United States--Societies and clubs.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Detroit.; Civic leaders--Michigan--Detroit.; Governors' spouses--Michigan.; Brucker, Clara H.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Personal and biographical
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Papers, Hantel estate (Box 1)
  - Brucker and Hantel genealogical and miscellaneous materials (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (include notes of interview conducted by Robert Warner with her assessment of the personalities she encountered while her husband was Secretary of the Army), June 15, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1921-1923, 1930-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1978, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
  - Tributes to Wilber Brucker and related dedicatory material
    - Letters of condolence (sample), 1968 (Box 1)
    - Tributes to Wilber Brucker, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Tributes undated, and 1974-1975 to Wilber Brucker (Box 1)
    - Dedication Brucker Room, Bentley Historical Library, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Dedication Brucker Hall, Fort Myer, Virginia, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Madame Chiang Kai-shek, 1956-1976; 2 folders (Box 1)
- School of Government, 1945-1978
  - Correspondence
    - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960, 1976; 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Purpose (Box 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Board of Directors, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous resolutions, 1952; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Resolution, concerning protection of women and children, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous committee reports, 1940; 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Annual report
    - Educational director, undated; 1944-1953; 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - President, 1942; 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer, 1959-1968 (Box 1)
    - Recording secretary, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Membership lists, 1952-1959 (Box 2)
  - Membership yearbook
    - 1942-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1965, 1966; 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter, 1954-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Programs, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Speeches by Mrs. Brucker, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Speeches 1958, 1960 by others (Box 2)
  - May Day luncheon, undated; 1946-1953; 1962-1968 (Box 2)
  - Clippings Countess Alexandra Tolstoy, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 2)
- Women's civic, political and service organizations, 1942-1978; undated
  - Mock Republican Convention
    - Miscellanea, Undated (Box 2)
    - 1940 (Box 2)
    - 1944 (Box 2)
    - 1948, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1952 (Box 2)
  - Speeches by Mrs. Brucker to various women's clubs (Box 2)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs
    - Correspondence, 1955; 1962 (Box 2)
    - Papers, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - Women's City Club of Detroit
    - Papers, 1963; 1965-1978 (Box 2)
    - Magazine, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Presbyterian Church Women's Group Speech by Mrs. Brucker, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Federation of Republican Women
    - Membership yearbooks, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
    - Administration Liaison Committee reports, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - Speeches by Mrs. Brucker, 1956-1960 (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Children's Aid Society 1945-1948, 1971, 1976-1977 including minutes, 1945-1977 (Box 2)
  - Prevention and Enforcement of sex crimes against women and children
    - Correspondence, 1953; 1955 (Box 2)
    - Committee lists, 1953; 1955 (Box 2)
    - Articles 1946, 1950, 1957 sexual crimes, 1946-1957 (Box 2)
    - Report Governor's Commission on Deviated Sex Offender, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Morality in media, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Morality in media of Michigan
    - Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, undated; 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Knights Templar, 1968-1978 (Box 2)
  - International Neighbors Club, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Wolverine Girl's State, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Rainbow Division Auxiliary, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Grosse Pointe War Memorial Association, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Papers miscellaneous charities, 1956-1960 (Box 2)
  - Red Cross, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Salvation Army, 1951; 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Northwood Institute, National Women's Board
    - Correspondence, 1971-1979 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, 1970-1978 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters, undated (Box 3)
    - Membership lists, undated (Box 3)
    - Fun Auction Day, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - Starr Commonwealth for Boys 1949, 1957, 1969, 1974-1977 Correspondence (sample), 1949-1977 (Box 3)
  - Walker and Gertrude Cisler Library, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Speeches by others, 1960-1973 (Box 3)
  - Speeches by Mrs. Brucker
    - To Michigan State University, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 3)
  - Papers 1922, 1935 by Mrs. Brucker (Box 3)
  - Notable American Women 1932, 1945 articles by Mrs. Brucker (Box 3)
  - Notable women of Northwood Institute, 1972 (Box 3)
- Clippings
  - General Douglas McArthur, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Hart-Romney senate campaign, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Travel and trip briefings
  - Okinawa, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Europe, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Seventh U.S. Army inspection, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Alaska, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Far East, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Western United States, 1962; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Travel letters Mabel Slocum, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Trip Scandinavia, Russia, Germany and Italy, 1969 (Box 3)
- Diaries
  - 1954-1960 (Box 7)
  - 1954-1960 (Box 8)
    (continued)
  - Various dates (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook (Box 4)
  - Book: Johann Adam Brucker and His American Descendents by Wallace H. Brucker (1978). (Box 4)
  - Appointment books (sampled) (Box 5)
  - Courtship letters exchanged between Wilber Brucker and Clara Hantel, 1920-1923 (Box 6)
  - Letters exchanged between Wilber and Clara Brucker, 1940; 1948; 1955 (Box 6)
  - Letters exchanged with Mrs. Orin Bradford (Box 6)
  - Letters re. Wilber Brucker's papers (including letters from Dwight Eisenhower) (Box 6)